This is Los Angeles, the second largest
city in the United [music] States and
the cultural capital of the world. And
this was once the most extensive transit
system ever built. A network of street
cars, [music] more than a,000 m long.
2,000 trains that ran daily, linking
neighborhoods across Southern
California.
>> The [music] sad truth is we once had one
of the finest transit systems around. It
was called the [music] Pacific Electric
Railway. Today, it's almost
unimaginable. Good quality, space
efficient transit in a city that's known
for some of the [music] worst traffic on
the planet.
>> Hardly a year goes by that somebody
doesn't come up with still another plan
to bring [music] rapid transit to
Southern California. Yet, so far, all
we've got is buses that are no more
rapid than your average family car.
>> For years, street cars carried families
from their houses through orange groves
to the [music] cities. Today, their
descendants do the same, but stuck in
their cars for hours. A century ago,
street cars transformed LA from nothing
into America's second largest city.
>> Relive the final years of the [music]
Los Angeles street car system, fondly
remembered by older Angelinos as the
yellow cars. You'll return to the year
1956 to visit all of the [music]
remaining street car lines in service
and follow them through to 1963 and
their [music] final abandonment. But
then they disappeared.
This is the [music] story of one of the
greatest railway battles in American
history. It's a story about the man who
built LA street cars, and it's the story
of why they vanished.
1874, a judge named Robert Whitney built
the first public transit in LA, a single
horse car track. [music]
LA was a small farming town, a handful
of streets. But when the railroads came,
the population boomed. Horse car lines
sprang up around the city. People wanted
the market. [music]
But they didn't just make their money by
selling tickets. They made money by
selling land. They divided tracks into
parcels, graded them, and supplied them
with water. Then they built transit. The
lots rose in value. People could commute
to consume or [music] open businesses.
These neighborhoods were called street
car suburbs. Many cities where
everything could be reached within 15
minutes. one of America's most
traditional ways of building. They built
[music] mixeduse buildings as well as a
variety of low and medium density
housing types. Apartments, duplexes,
forplexes, bungalow courts, and single
family homes. Many buildings that are
illegal to build today. Streets were
planned in a grid. The block lengths
were short and sidewalks [music] were
fronted by multi-story businesses. They
built shaded arcades and ornamented
facades to give people something nice to
look at as they walked around. The ones
that survived intact are some of the
most desirable neighborhoods in the
entire United States.
Prudin Bodri came to California during
the gold rush. He started a business in
San Francisco [music] selling shovels,
but it failed after fires burned all of
it. So, he moved to LA. He bought land
like the others and started developing.
He owned some hilly tracks near
downtown, but it was still too steep to
access [music] by horse car. He wanted
to make a profit on his land. He needed
a way to move people up the slopes.
Horse cars wouldn't [music] work. But
Bodri had an answer from San Francisco.
Cable cars. At their peak, they ran 17
hours a day with one coming every 5
minutes. Most of the energy went into
the winding machinery and the cables,
which had to be replaced and were heavy.
They were superior [music] to horse
cars, but they weren't reliable.
Luckily, in 1888, there was a
breakthrough miles away on the other
side of the country. Richmond, Virginia,
built America's [music] first citywide
electric street car. A power plant
generated direct current [music] sent
through an overhead wire. Each street
car collected this power with a roof
mounted trolley pole and sent it to
onboard motors that powered the axles.
[music] Then, current returned through
the rails to complete the circuit. It
spread like wildfire. By 1890, Charlie
started replacing cable cars [music]
across the country, and they were coming
to LA.
But they never got there because they
were too busy playing World of Warships.
World of Warships is free to play and
easy to jump into with friends. Hundreds
of historically inspired warships.
[music] From destroyers and cruisers to
battleships, carriers, and submarines
with updated visuals and new content
landing every month. America [music]
just turned 250 and the game is
celebrating with a US anniversary event
running through July 15th. Each week
unlocks narrative stages, historical
paintings, and rewards along the path to
American independence. Play a single
battle and you get a free anniversary
bundle on top. Click the first link in
the description and use code USA250.
Whether you're new or returning, you'll
get a million credits, a week of
premium, and two premium American ships,
the cruiser Albany, and the destroyer
Smith. It's also on console as World of
Warships, Legends.
Moses Hazeline Sherman saw the potential
of the new electric trolleys. He'd
earned a fortune in Arizona, but he was
convinced LA was the real jackpot. In
1890, he started a company that built
multiple street car lines across LA.
When his competitors went bankrupt, he
bought them up. He consolidated 35 mi of
electric lines, [music]
21 mi of cable lines, and 14 mi of
horsear lines. This became [music] the
yellow car system. Moses would own the
largest street car railway operation in
LA, but he got too greedy. And there was
another man who saw lane track as a way
to fortune, and he was coming for the
yellow cars. Henry Huntington was no
small man. His uncle was one of the big
four [music] that built the
transcontinental railroad. After his
uncle died, Henry expected to take
control of his vast railroad empire, but
he was betrayed. A group of Southern
Pacific shareholders blocked Henry from
ascending to the presidency.
Uncompromising, he sold his shares for
$50 million. The buyer was a man named
Eh Haramman. Heramman was one of the
guilded age Robert Barons, known as the
little giant of Wall Street. He was
actually a kind of small man, but big in
the rail business. Henry was furious at
the [music] South Pacific, so he took
his millions to Los Angeles. If he
couldn't have his uncle Southern [music]
Pacific Empire, he would have to build
his own. When Sherman was late on his
bond payments, Henry used the
opportunity to buy the entire yellow car
system. And he wasn't done. By 1902, his
company started building its own lines.
Pacific Electric's first new line ran to
Long Beach. The red cars were [music]
electric. They were newer, faster,
cleaner, and more frequent than Southern
Pacific trains. But they also had an
owner driven more by spite than capital.
Henry Huntington didn't care about
profits. Every extra cent earned was
invested back into building new lines.
Huntington wanted revenge [music] for
being kicked out of Southern Pacific,
and he was going to try and take them
out of business. But they saw that he
was coming, and Heramman wasn't going to
go easily. Henry built his tracks next
to Southern Pacific routes. With his
faster standard gauge trains, he could
compete with Southern [music] Pacific's
freight shipping and steal their
passengers. But Southern Pacific wasn't
blind.
In 1903, Haramman made a move to level
[music] the playing field. He purchased
an entire rail company called the Hook
Line, big enough to directly compete in
LA. Herman had deeper pockets, but
Huntington didn't care. [music]
When a rail franchise went up for
auction, both of them went for it. The
bids kept going higher and higher. A
franchise worth $5,000 doubled in value,
then tripled, then tripled again, and
sold to Haramman. [music]
Huntington was defeated. He couldn't
compete against Haramman's wallet. In a
peace deal, Haramman [music] was given a
joint stake in Pacific Electric.
Huntington was forced to accept his
rival as a business partner with Veto
Power on the company [music] board.
But he and Heramman clashed constantly
with competing priorities. [music]
Huntington wanted to run passenger lines
to his empty, undeveloped lots. For him,
the rail line was a loss leader. He was
willing to take on debt as long as his
land went up in value. But Haramman was
the head of a transcontinental shipping
empire. He wanted the Pacific Electric
to profit on freight shipping and
reliable ticket sales and established
towns. Haramman could veto anything that
went against his interest. Huntington
wanted to build a line to San Diego
County for a new development, but Herman
vetoed it because it competed with his
own plans. Frustrated, Huntington
established a new railroad company, the
Los Angeles Inter urban with full
ownership and built new routes from Los
Angeles to Orange County. The business
arrangement wasn't working. Southern
Pacific and Huntington agreed to another
deal. Huntington got a cash payout and
the yellow car that let him focus on
real estate. and Southern Pacific
[music] got the Red Car, the largest
ledger transit system in the world. It
linked more than 50 communities across
four counties, Los Angeles, [music]
Riverside, San Bernardino, and Orange.
At its peak in 1924, 2,000 daily trains
ran on 1,100 [music]
m of track, more track mileage than
Germany's highspeed rail system today,
more than the combined lengths of all
Shinkansen lines north of Tokyo, and
even more route length than the modern
New York City subway, London
Underground, and Paris Metro systems
combined. But then they disappeared.
It's the 1980s. An investigative
journalist named Jonathan Quinty finds
something in a Chicago warehouse. Two
battered cartons covered in dust. Inside
are transcripts, testimonials, and
filings from a forgotten 1949 court
case. United States v National City
Lines. [music]
He discovers something. In 1933, a man
from General Motors approached a man
named Leroy [music] Fitzgerald, a 7th
grade dropout who was operating a small
Minnesota bus service with his brothers.
Young, ambitious, and small [music]
enough to be controlled, the man offered
Fitzgerald a deal that was too good to
pass up.
>> We'll invest in your [music] company.
We'll finance your acquisitions, help
you with technical surveys and
negotiations. We'll give you financial
backing, anything you need. But we do
need one thing in return. With our
money, you're going to buy street car
companies in small cities, and you'll
replace all of them with our buses.
>> Fitzgerald couldn't believe his ears. He
was going to be a very wealthy man. All
he had to do was go along with General
Motors his scheme. They helped him
establish a holding company called
National City Lines. Then with GM
funding, Fitzgerald bought out and
dismantled electric street car networks
in city after city. He started small,
Illinois, Gillsburg, East St. Louis, and
Juliet. [music]
As his business growth started to appear
more legitimate, he moved on to
Oklahoma, Alabama, Texas, and Iowa. He
and General Motors took [music] over but
Montana then Lincoln Nebraska. The
scheme worked so well that other [music]
corporations piled in to invest.
Firestone Tire and Rubber, Philips
Petroleum, and strangely Mac Trucks,
General Motors direct competitor.
Fitzgerald took [music] over Salt Lake
City, Portland, Tampa, and Mobile. They
ripped out the street cars [music] and
signed contracts to buy buses built by
General Motors with Firestone tires that
ran on standard oil diesel. [music]
One by one, Baltimore, El Paso, and
Spokane all fell to Fitzgerald and
General Motors. Then they set their
sights on the biggest transit system of
all, Los Angeles.
[music] In 1947, the Justice Department
caught on. They filed an antitrust
lawsuit. The conspirators were found
guilty of one charge to monopolize the
sale of buses and supplies. [music]
Their contracts with transit companies
to exclusively buy their products was
ruled illegal, but the defendants were
acquitted of the charge to monopolize
transportation itself. The penalty was a
slap on the wrist. The oil and auto
companies were each fined $5,000.
Individual company officials were fined
$1 each. But when Quinty reviewed the
case files, it didn't make sense. If
they were just building buses, why would
General Motors go into [music] business
with its direct competitor, Mac Trucks?
Their goal wasn't just to profit on bus
fairs and bus supplies alone. The only
way to make it make sense is if bus
revenue was secondary to the sale of
automobiles after the street cars were
killed. After the tracks were paved
over, General Motors profited by selling
cars. Mack by selling trucks. The
economics are obvious. One bus can
eliminate 35 automobiles. One street
car, subway, or rail transit vehicle can
supplant 50 passenger cars. One train
can displace 1,000 cars or a fleet of
150 cargo laden trucks. A coordinated
scheme to systematically accelerate
carcentric development and replace
trains and transit with traffic. But the
street car companies were already having
problems before General Motors came. By
the 1920s, the Los Angeles basin was
producing 20% of the global supply of
oil. Cheap local fuel caused more cars
to appear on LA roads. They became a
symbol of the American dream. As
industry boomed, more people flocked to
the city. Demand for land rose.
Speculators assumed that holding and
subdividing land would generate return
on investment as land values continued
to rise.
Speculative real estate finance helped
set the stage for the Great Depression.
Before, banks expected a 50% down
payment for a home with a balloon
payment for the rest of the loan due at
the end of a 5-year term. But in the
Great Depression, banks were desperate
for cash. They wouldn't allow people to
extend the balloon payment. When they
couldn't pay, the banks seized the
homes. Shanty towns appeared across the
country. Congress passed the National
Housing Act and created the Federal
Housing Administration. They'd ensure
banks when homeowners couldn't pay. It
actively promoted home ownership by
guaranteeing a federal backing for home
loans with long payback periods. To
reduce [music] their risk on these
longer mortgages, the FHA used
color-coded maps made by the Homeowners
Loan Corporation. They pushed loans away
from areas flagged as hazardous for
investment and wealthier all-white
homogeneous suburban areas were seen as
safe. In order for people to qualify for
loans with federal backing, urban
planners and developers mandated strict
zoning, uniform housing types, and
requirements for lot sizes and setbacks.
They put restrictions on subdividing
lots or building new dwellings and
required approval by committee for any
new building [music] designs. They
actively steered for cookie cutter
single family suburbs that were designed
for cars, not dense transit. While
Huntington risked his own capital to go
in direct competition with Southern
Pacific and bring down prices, the state
directly funded freeways that were built
alongside the railway [music] corridors.
As cars became more affordable, the
problem for street cars spiraled. As
they increased on the same roads, street
cars had to compete for space. They got
stuck in traffic and they weren't able
to make their schedules, sometimes
running 30 minutes late. They used to go
40 or 50 mph, but now slowed down into
the 10s. Then there was falling
ridership, which meant declining
revenue. Declining revenue and the
quality of service got even worse. In
1944, [music] they reached a breaking
point. The yellow car was sold to
Fitzgerald, who followed the GM playbook
to rip out the lines and [music] replace
them with buses. In 1947, Pacific
Electric made one last ditch effort,
asking the city and state for a ride
ofway [music] in the center of the under
construction Hollywood Freeway. With a
fully owned road, their cars wouldn't
get stuck in traffic, and they wouldn't
be able to transport twice as many
people per hour as eight lanes of cars.
For those who valued speed and no
congestion, this was an obvious bargain.
But the proposal was rejected because it
interfered with freeway construction.
The urban planners started to look at
the redline areas as urban blight that
needed to be demolished. The bunker hill
tracks developed by prudent bodri were
once wealthy, but the mansions were
subdivided. They house low-income
residents and businesses that sprang
from the community. They gave the poor
access to valuable land and commerce
through [music] small units. But it was
marked as high risk on the redlinining
map. In 1949, it was bulldozed to build
the stack, the world's first four-level
stack interchange, connecting the new
Hollywood Freeway with the Royo Seiko.
The rest of Bunker Hill was bulldozed in
the 50s and60s [music] as part of more
slum clearance policies. Just to the
north, the government forcibly evicted
1,800 [music] families from the Chavez
Ravine to build Dodger Stadium for a
baseball team that used to be called the
Charlie [music] Dodgers.
One by one, the street car lines were
closed and the tracks were ripped out.
The last red car on the Long Beach line,
the first line built by Pacific
Electric, made its final trip in 1961.
Almost immediately, the city realized
its mistakes. They tried to raise $500
million to rebuild a rail system. But by
the time of the oil crisis, the cost of
constructing 116 mi of track, less than
1/6 the size of the red car, rose from
500 million to more than [music] $6.6
billion.
The tradition of storefronts attached to
the sidewalks was over. Businesses and
houses were required to have parking
lots in front of detached buildings. By
the 1970s, more than half of [music] Los
Angeles was zoned exclusively for single
family homes.
[music]
What was once a dream is fast becoming a
reality.
The long- aaited metro rail is on track
and headed for Los Angeles.
>> In 1980, the city passed Proposition A,
a half cent sales tax to fund a new
metro.
When it arrives not long from now, Metro
Rail will prove to be the vital link
[music] to providing a muchneeded
balanced transportation system for the
area. A total system that complements
our comprehensive network [music] of
buses and freeways and one that will
foster the growth, vitality, and
economic development of this
international metropolis, Los Angeles. A
decade later, a new light rail opened.
The blue A-ine followed the original red
car route to [music] Long Beach. In
1993, the red beline opened, LA's first
modern subway. For the past three
decades, LA has been on a transit
building spree. And now, Los Angeles is
constructing more new rail than any
other city in the United States.
The 28x28 initiative is trying to
complete 28 infrastructure projects in
time for the next summer Olympic Games.
A two-mile regional connector has
already been added downtown. A new
transit [music] hub was built at the
airport and a new 9mm extension of the
Purple D line is currently under
construction. Ironically, after 100
years, LA is returning to a traditional
way of building. Senate Bill 79
overrides the zoning laws [music] and
parking minimums that made it illegal to
rebuild density along the transit
corridor. Thousands of new homes are
planned in a city with a severe housing
deficit. Los Angeles has a long way to
go, but maybe one day it could once
again have the greatest transit system
in the world.